Muhammad Alkali Muawiya

SUMMARY

I am a highly motivated and dedicated individual with robust knowledge of agile methodologies, particularly scrum. I have experience working remotely and understand the importance of good communication. With strong problem-solving skills and efficient time management, I have designed and implemented software solutions for various business needs. My expertise lies in Node.js development, and I have a successful track record in industries such as healthcare and entertainment. As a proactive engineer and leader, I excel in collaborative environments and bring a strong work ethic to every task.

EXPERIENCE

Decagon, Lagos Nigeria — Software Engineer

JUNE 2020 - Date

- Developed and maintained web applications using web development concepts such as HTTP, REST, GraphQL, and MVC architecture, utilizing TypeScript to write clean, efficient, and well-documented code.
- Built and managed databases using database management systems such as SQL and MongoDB.
- Implemented DevOps tools and methodologies such as Docker to improve application deployment and scalability.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams including product managers, designers, and other developers to build new features and enhance existing ones.
- Ensured the performance, security, and reliability of web applications by implementing best practices and testing strategies and staying up-to-date with emerging trends, technologies, and development practices in the web development field.

Techvibes International Ltd, Abuja Nigeria — User Experience

JUNE 2019 - JUNE 2020

- Gathered and wrote reports on product requirements: Played a crucial role in understanding client needs and specifications, ensuring a clear understanding of product requirements for software development.
- Conducted quality assessments: Identified and documented problems in software products, working closely with the technical team to propose effective solutions, and improve the overall quality and user experience.
- Monitored and reported user feedback: After launching software, actively collected and analyzed users' reactions and feedback, enabling continuous improvement of the user experience.
- Provided support and training: Assisted both internal and external users by providing support and training, ensuring their successful utilization of the software, and addressing any questions or issues they encountered.

ADDRESS

Nepa Close, Off Ahmadu Bello Way, Victoria Island, 101241, Lagos Nigeria. +2347060702020

muawiyamuhd@gmail.com LinkedIn Profile URL Github Profile URL Portfolio URL

TECHNOLOGIES & SKILLS

- Node.js
- Express.js
- React.js
- JavaScript
- TypeScript
- Docker
- SQL
- MongoDB
- GraphQL
- REST API
- Git & Github
- Teams
- Slack
- Iira
- Scrum

OTHER EXPERIENCE

Appen, UK (Remote) — Freelancer

FEBRUARY 2020 - AUGUST 2021

Search Engine Evaluator

- Evaluated and analyzed search engine results based on specific guidelines and criteria.
- Provided feedback on the accuracy and relevance of search engine algorithms and results.
- Stayed updated with the latest search engine trends and guidelines to improve evaluation accuracy.

Social Media Evaluator

- Assessed and evaluated the quality and relevance of social media content and advertisements.
- Provided feedback on social media trends, user behavior, and engagement to enhance algorithms and ad targeting.
- Identified and reported any content or policy violations observed during the evaluation process.

Transcriptionist

- Accurately transcribing audio or video content while following transcription guidelines.
- Maintaining high-quality transcripts with accurate grammar, punctuation, and formatting.
- Meeting project deadlines and productivity targets while ensuring attention to detail and maintaining confidentiality.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Docker for the absolute beginner
 Credential
- Introduction to Cyber Security
- EF SET English Proficiency Credential
- Scrum Fundamentals Certified (SFC) Credential
- Accelerated Jobberman Soft Skills Credential

PROJECTS

E-Aid

E-Aid(a First-Aid app) allows users to have access to verified medical experts through the app. It allows the users to see the hospitals closest to them and help them to get expert advice in the case of an emergency. Technologies used include Express.js, Typescript, MySQL, Sequelize, React, AWS, Docker, Cloudinary, Nodemailer, and CSS3. Link: https://e-aid-66j7.onrender.com

MovieVerse

MovieVerse is a movie listing app where registered users can add, edit and delete movies with titles, images, prices and brief descriptions. It offers a user-friendly interface to manage the movie list easily. Technologies used include Express.js, Typescript, MongoDB, Mongoose, Docker, and EJS. Link: https://movie-verse.onrender.com

FitMind

A health-tech app that connects clients with verified physical fitness experts and therapists. Technologies used include Express.js, Typescript, Sqlite, Sequelize, and React. Link: https://github.com/MM-Alkali/FitMind.git

My Portfolio

A responsive Single Page Application that showcases my skills and projects as a software developer. Technologies used include; HTML, CSS and Vanilla JavaScript. **Link**: https://www.mmalkali.me

EDUCATION

Modibbo Adama University of Technology, Yola Nigeria

DECEMBER 2012 - MAY 2019

First Class Honours - Bachelor of Technology (Hons) in Biochemistry Best Graduating Student of the Department and Faculty, 2017/2018